ESTHER F. N. MAINA CV

Nairobi, Kenya | + (254) 721 634961 | estherfaithnjoki@mail.com

SUMMARY

A highly experienced administrator with over six years of teaching experience, with a solid academic grounding: a master's in Research and Public Policy, a BA in Political Science and Communication, and an ongoing PhD. In Public Policy.

WORK EXPERIENCE

TEACHING

Oct. 2023 to Date University Teaching

University of Nairobi - Nairobi, Kenya

A part-time lecturer in the Political Science and Public Administration department.

- Collating teaching material as guided by the course descriptions
- Teaching undergraduate students, both online and on-site.
- Supervising undergraduate examinations.
- Marks entry into the examination system.

Oct. 2016-Feb. 2021 Technical College Teaching

Kips Technical College - Nairobi, Kenya

Served as a Lecturer and a Head of Department-Journalism and Media Studies

- Incorporated interactive elements to promote student engagement in learning.
- Created and implemented successful mentoring initiatives for students in the Journalism/Communication department.
- Led a range of workshops, lectures, and seminars for the enlightenment and engagement of Journalism/Communications students.
- Assumed responsibility as a student advisor/mentor, supporting and guiding over 50 students during my tenure.

RESEARCH

Jan.-Feb. 2024 RESEARCH ASSISTANT

NORDIC AFRICA INSTITUTE-Sweden Assignment

Undertook a Study on "Making Politics Safer-Gendered Violence and Electoral Temporalities in Africa".

- Research's contact persons lead.
- Engaged in interviewing relevant organizations and institutions' contact persons for the project.
- Engaged in conducting interviews with 'Women in Politics' in Nairobi, Nakuru and Uasin Gishu Counties, Kenya.
- Interview transcription.
- Co-authoring underway.

March 2023 RESEARCHER

DATA WORLD (Ngo)

A study on 'Women empowerment for electoral positions'

Successfully carried out a data collection exercise on women who
unsuccessfully vied for a member of parliament positions in the Counties of
Nakuru, Kajiado, and Kirinyaga Counties in Kenya, to facilitate assessment
and addressing challenges facing women politicians in competitive politics.

Oct. 2022 RESEARCH LEAD

Ministry of Water, Sanitation and Irrigation, Kenya

Study on 'Water Sector Skills and Competency Assessment and Development of Related Framework Research'

- Spearheaded a multi-disciplinary team to conduct comprehensive research on skills and competency in the water sector
- Designed and executed research methodologies including focus group discussions, key informant interviews, and general interviews
- Managed data collection, and data analysis, and ensured the quality and integrity of data
- Coordinated with stakeholders from government agencies, educational institutions, and private sector organizations
- Prepared and presented research findings to advisory committees and other key stakeholders.

COMMUNITY ENGAGEMENT AND ADVOCACY

03/2022 to date Oslo Center, Kirinyaga County Chapter, Kenya

- Actively involved in initiatives aimed at bringing together women candidates vying for political positions under the umbrella of small parties in Kirinyaga County, Kenya.
- Spearheading community-level empowerment programs that focus on gender mainstreaming and youth active involvement in the political space.
- Collaborating with local and national stakeholders to create platforms for women in politics and drive conversations on gender issues.

2021-to-date KARITI 'PICK-ME-UP' INITIATIVE

- A mentorship, Guidance and Counseling Initiative that works with teenage mothers supporting them to go back to school in line with Kenya's 'Readmission Policy for Teenage Mothers'.
- It is a collaborative effort with politically elected leaders in my community. We have supported six student mothers since 2021 to date to go back to high school and sit their final year examinations.

ADMINISTRATOR

Sept. 2009 SKIZAH MEDIA COMPANY

Aug. 2014

- Led public relations and communications strategy for a rapidly growing business- including guiding the firm's vision and narrative development.
- Developed strong relationships with top-tier members of the media, resulting in positive editorial coverage for the organization.
- Represented the organization at national conferences, providing valuable insights to a wide range of audiences.

- Built long-term relationships with key stakeholders, enabling the organization to interact with customers in a meaningful way and meet overall objectives.
- Day-to-day running of the office.

EDUCATION

2022-On going PhD. in Public Policy

University of Nairobi - Nairobi, Kenya

2018-2020

Master of Research and Public Policy

(MRPP)

University of Nairobi - Nairobi, Kenya

2013-2016 BA-Political Science and Public Administration/Communication

University of Nairobi - Nairobi, Kenya

PUBLICATIONS

- Rethinking Democracy: Elections; Past, Present and Future, 'How Would Kenya Look Like Under Proportional Representation? A publication of the Konrad-Adenauer-Stiftung;
 https://www.kas.de/documents/286528/0/Rethinking+Democracy.pdf/c47e69a1-ab2a-7b10-ca48-daf4771b499d?t=1580291244526.
- Njoki, E. F. (2020). Policy, Perception, and Socio-cultural Determinants of Male Involvement in Female Contraceptive Uptake: A Case of Korogocho, Nairobi County.
 http://repository.uonbi.ac.ke/handle/11295/154035 (Masters Thesis)

SKILLS

- Academia: General class teaching
- Management: Organized, time-conscious, analytical, and leadership
- Articulate: Proficient in the English language, both written and spoken
- Research: Data Collection
- Report Writing.

- Communication skills
- Deadline management
- Rapport building
- Data analysis- Qualitatively, and Quantitatively using Excel, SPSS and STATA